[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defus and
welcome to holot talk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's
[Music]
show hi Mark it's Frank Deus hey Frank
how are you doing pretty good good to
finally talk to you it's great to talk
to you I've been reading uh all the
whole talk or listening to the H talks
for uh gosh since you started with with
your 27 years that you've been been
involved with this even if we were to
condense each year down to a minute
we're still looking at a half hour so
that's funny to go back 27 years I mean
people that are listening to the show
number one a lot of them weren't even
born yet okay and number two you're
going back to a time when you just
didn't go out and purchase a laser and
go in your basement and do Holograms
because it was such an expensive
purchase I mean it was a thing of was
science fiction 27 years ago on the
street at least not to us but on the
street what got you started in this well
I guess it's saw my first hologram when
I was 12 years old at an art festival
down here and they were from the
Smithsonian they were transmission types
so they're all played back by laser my
dad took me to the show and the thing
that totally knocked my socks out I was
a photographer at the time and uh was
the fact that there was a a picture of a
book with a magnifying glass and you
could actually move around and see the
magnifying glass lens the words in the B
book that didn't make any sense to me as
a photographer and kind of stashed in
the back of my mind and then fast
forward about four or five years ago I
read an article in the New York Times
written by a lady named Peggy seon a
photography writer about the New York
school of holography opening and I just
decided Well you know D the Torpedoes I
need to go and find out what that's all
about yeah and so I got on a plane and
went up there and uh and studied and uh
just got bitten by the bug was that that
one of those first exhibits that was in
New York at the time well the very very
first exibit was before the Museum per
se yeah was around and it was over at I
International Center of Photography yeah
but uh it wasn't so much an exhibit but
they were teaching down in the basement
where later Dan and Sam so famously
taught on 13th Street New York school
holography it was posie Jackson Jody
Burns yeah uh were running it and uh
although they weren't my instructors or
anything so I came back and a B I told
my mom you know I was going to buy a
laser and and she had you know visions
of Dr No and you know James Bond and all
that and thought I was going to burn a
hole through the house and this is the
early 70s right yeah and uh so uh got a
laser built a little laser lab started
re uh redoing all the experiments that
i' had read people had done that I just
couldn't believe the results of so that
was a lot of fun then about six months
later went back to New York with the
stuff this is before the museum opened
and I showed some of the stuff to to
posy and you know she kind of flipped
out in a positive way and sent jod off
to find me some Jun giant AGA plates to
me they were giant they were 11 by 14
inch plates yeah I said do this this
size we want to show this at the opening
of Museum holography and I was like oh
my God you know I've never seen a plate
so big in my life I've been working with
8 by10 and 4x5 yeah and uh one piece in
particular that they like although we
ended up showing three at the Museum's
opening and and I helped around there
sweep the floors Bolt the you know sign
on the wall and you know tweak lasers
and secure lasers Scurry Scurry around
Edmond scientific across the
cross the river and trying to find the
bits and parts we could Cobble together
what we needed to to to show off the big
transmission types that were on loan to
the museum which were oh just a jooy I
mean the big portrait of Gabor
everyone's seen portrait and some of the
classic Fritz Goro stuff and some early
McDonald Douglas stuff you know these
are meter some OD size transmission
types which at the time seemed you know
gargantuan so we set those up to
playback by laser along with all the
rest of the stuff at the Museum and it
was a very heady time because uh uh well
for God's sakes for me it was like home
because out here on the peninsula there
was nobody doing this between here and
New York and uh so it was like home to
me the fact that a place actually gave
me and the work and the medium enough
respect to uh to establish a a you know
a museum I was just really touched by
the whole thing and it was it was very
uh it was wonderful did you have a piece
in that in augural uh tour I thing it
was called through the looking glass or
something when the museum first open
yeah well the first opening show down
there uh at the Museum there were three
one was curved space time uh one was
Holo Dolly uh a holographic uh um
portrait of Sal Dolly that's frozen
inside this multifaceted Crystal and the
third one was something called uh uh
geometric Optical graphic design is
observed through Crystal Bobble floating
in foreground and basically it was a
hologram where this giant multifaceted
Bobble did FL float about a foot in
front of the plate and you could walk up
to it and uh and put your eye up to it
and see this geometric design behind it
being lensed like hundreds of times
through the bottle so its lensing
function was was captured I believe it
in that first show we did a lot of uh
placing of uh little stickers on the
ground uh where sort of like you know
those games where they show you how to
tango or whatever okay and where where
to put your feet or whatever oh yeah
yeah yeah and it was kind of
instructions on how to the Hologram
because people weren't unfamiliar with
how to address the space yeah and we're
so used to we've grown up you know with
this whole lasow Gutenberg tradition of
everything is either on the cave wall or
in the book or on the TV screen
everything is flat and so uh you have to
kind of relearn how to look at universe
as a multi-dimensional entity that that
it was in the first place when you were
born you well you know from my
observations being out at exhibits I
think we could still use those
footprints on the floors now oh yeah no
no especially with projected images you
know projected images are are a
situation where you don't know what to
expect if you're not you know Savvy yeah
that was an early show it actually uh
when I went on the road I stopped in
Philadelphia at the Walnut Street
Theater trying to think of the year was
probably mid 70s or so cuz I remember um
I went down I had a car that had one of
the windows was broken out and I had
plastic on the window and there was no
heat in the car so we were wrapped in
blankets as we waited in the parking lot
we don't know from that down here in
Miami by the way oh yeah yeah you'd know
it today up here interesting yeah so you
do a lot of other things now I'm going
to have a link to your website oh that's
sweet you know along with the uh the
show as well so when people come to
listen to the show and in fact if you're
listening to the show now there's no
reason to sit there and just stare at
the computer you know real player will
play in the background so if you go back
on the holot talk page and click on the
diamond images link you'll be able to go
right to the website while you listen to
it as well you know providing you can do
two things at once which most of you I
assume can um to move on you've always
been in Florida I guess then right well
based here yeah I've worked in different
places but I I'm based here in Miami and
I'm kind of a a Tropic subtropical kind
of guy and don't really want to shovel
snow Yeah they they visitors definitely
have to go on to your experience page as
far as where you list all the things
that you've done I mean you've been a
photographer for Rolling Stone magazine
back in the days I imagine it was the
newspaper back thing cuz I remember
getting newpaper format that's correct
yeah yeah no I've done photo journalism
in in many years yeah that was uh kind
of grew up telling stories with pictures
you know using two-dimensional images
but when I bumped into holography it
opened up a whole another realm as you
can imagine yeah well this this is the
real deal with you I mean a lot of the
people that uh listen to the show are
are amateurs and hobbyists you know and
well I can address amateurs and hobbyist
oh sure absolutely but you I can tell
them the one most inspiring thing that
I've discovered great go ahead it
doesn't make any difference whether
you're 15 years old 8 years old or 55 or
80 years old the next Dr Dennis Gabor
the next discovery of significant import
perhaps a window into yet another
dimension will come from someone
regardless of their age who's paying
very close attention yeah absolutely and
that's the interesting thing uh
throughout the history of Science and
the whole so-called serendipitous
discoveries and and that sort of thing
somebody was paying real close
attention and uh uh that's one very
interesting factor that you don't need
to have all the degrees and you don't
need to necessarily be doing this 10
years or 20 years you might be doing it
you stumble upon something if you're
paying close attention to realize what
it is you've stumbled upon yeah yeah and
with some of the new light sources I
wouldn't be surprised if we see
something come down the PIP quickly that
uh takes the place of the laser period I
mean I know we've moved into the laser
diodes but when you start to look at
some of the LEDs and things of that
nature I wouldn't be surprised if they
start to get down to where they have
such I'm totally fascinated I've been
kind of predicting that for about 10
years ever since I had a student who
worked for op Electronics division of a
h Packard out and paloalto come in one
day when I was teaching out in San Jose
and he and he and he handed me a handful
of diodes that were at the time in the
red range and they were very narrow band
withd maybe about 10 nmet wide and he
was telling me that you know the blues
were coming and the or yellows were
coming and this was like 12 years ago
and at that point I realized that
perhaps it would be a Resurgence in
transmission types based on the fact the
light sources were going to cost a
dollar versus you know $500 or $1,000
and I think that's something that hasn't
really been properly exploited yet but
now that your guys are promoting things
like shoe box holography and the diode
stuff I have a feeling that uh that
that's going to be an obvious benefit of
of uh of cheap uh coherent or at least
monochromatic source is is the
Resurgence of the transmission type yeah
I love transmission Holograms I love
transmission Holograms yeah I've been
Illuminating a 30X 40 cm laser
transmission hologram down here now with
a uh a red LED that I got from Walmart
that cost like a
$1.99 very interesting yeah and it's
it's it's bright it's incredible yeah
yeah what what projects are you working
on now I know if they when when people
go to your website they'll be able to
see some of the ones that you've uh
worked on the Dizzy piece I have the
Dizzy piece you know uh down here
working there's always uh col train uh
Parker Monk and Davis on you know so I
have Holograms no no music oh music jazz
yeah so going back to yeah I want to see
that John cldr yeah uh going back to the
Dizzy hologram how did you get involved
with that well um di he uh in terms of
the creation of the Hologram and
everything um originally um I went to
see him and I uh perform here and I had
seen him a couple times never really
talked to him and uh I've been doing a
series of holograms ever since like the
mid late 7s uh of folks that I really
admired and he was one of them and and
uh actually really changed a lot in
terms of music and and awareness of
certainly the afro um realm of uh of a
African rhythms and stuff integrated
into into some of the so-called modern
music and anyway I I really admired him
I went and turns out he was a Shutterbug
uh he was really into photography and I
showed him some Holograms and and I
asked him uh if uh he would sit for me
and he said sure why not and as it
turned out um he was going to California
the next day and I was going to
California the next day too cuz I was
working on a hologram that we we mounted
aboard a a private J jet MH interior of
a private jet and so I was going out
there to work on the model for that and
and he was going out there so we decided
to do it out there and um uh uh that was
a Genesis of it basically I asked him if
he would sit for me and he said yeah
let's do it yeah so you you do that from
start to finish then that those pieces
right well I I what do you mean I mean I
at a facility in van at the the the film
capture again oh sure sure but for
instance the output of it was done uh I
filmed it with Greg newswanger
and uh back in uh gosh I don't remember
the year really but uh we were an
affility that they had I think at the
time they called it um I want to say add
but I know that that's something that
they that's something else these days uh
it was called Advanced dimensional
displays I believe okay and it was a
company that Craig and uh Chris Outwater
had had uh basically spawned after they
unplugged from Disney um that beautiful
facility that they put together for for
them and uh so it's very interesting how
sort of sideways uh Disney kind of Spawn
the creation of the of the system that
that that you know was making those
giant Holograms out there now of course
John car's the master you
know I think uh hands down as far as I'm
concerned what's the square footage of
your lab your fac right now I actually
work independently of running my own lab
I had put a facility together uh a few
years ago the last one I put together
was like three Labs uh it was huge and
it was 10,000 ft and um and we unplug
that lab and now uh without the overhead
of all that stuff I can work
independently uh with much greater
fluidity I found that over the years
people who had Labs specifically set up
to do one particular thing um had a
tendency to well only do that thing and
honestly with there's so many different
types of holograms that uh any given
project may require a specific type of
hologram and uh it's very hard to
maintain a facility that does all of
them well yeah so now I have incredible
uh uh um autonomy in terms of of of
specifying uh what is required for the
project and like I did a project a year
ago with this uh I guess it's world's
first smelling hologram uh which I shot
out with Eve and Ted out in uh in
Bordeaux and he of course is the fellow
who's been lauded as creating one of the
best full color emotions yeah beautiful
and uh but uh by circumstance that was
appropriate for this particular project
the smelling hologram he happened to
have a pulse laser uh uh Ruby there as
well as this other rig for creating the
full color stuff so they both worked
very well because I needed to uh
together because I needed to freeze
these uh candies and space for this
project
oh the Red Hots and while I had tried
all kinds of other way doing it that's a
great piece the best thing to do is just
to fly the candy in space grab it with
the pulse Ruby laser and then transfer
that Master to a white light feelable
reflection type that was ultimately in
the end the best way to do it
so now I can specify where to go for and
just basically Shepherd the project uh
in in a facility that doesn't belong to
me you know not I won't build another
lab it's just that for the moment
um I find a phenomenal autonomy and and
much lowered overhead on a day-to-day
basis yeah let let me just remind the
listeners that these Holograms that were
currently talking about both the dizzy
and and the red hot are uh both
available on your website for sale um go
over there check them out and uh I'm not
quite sure I don't I didn't see a price
on the Red Hots but I know it's a
limited edition of seven or something
right right but the Dizzy's an open an
open Edition no no no was Oh you mean
the giant one no the emboss oh the
little one yeah it's pretty much open
absolutely and those are I 20 bucks long
yeah yeah yeah history you sell a bunch
of those that's nice huh yeah it's a
piece of History it's fun uh you know I
always expected uh a time would come
when when we have this sort of
democratization of the art form in the
sense that you know why does someone
have to spend 100 or a th000 or $110,000
for a really nice piece of art uh in
this medium it's for 20 bucks bam you're
in and uh I think that's the way it
should be honestly I think all the best
Holograms in the world need to be
remastered for in a version that can be
purchased for 20 bucks oh yeah yeah you
go into some of holography shops and
you'll see a 4x5 piece of film in there
for like 50 bucks and someone will buy
one right but you'll never get them back
to buy a second one or that magic number
that you see always on TV 1995 yeah 1995
yeah that hologram God bless you for
that hologram you did of the Gloria uh I
I'd have to have a fan on me and go
outside and get some fresh air shooting
that yeah she she's a popping thing man
yeah and the stereoscopic view uh on
your web page is cool too because oh
it's funny how we struggle to try to
convey these things in 3D isn't it yeah
yeah yeah uh what other projects do you
have coming up well I've got you know a
whole uh set of them in various States
of uh of development uh since 1990 I've
been filming uh Native Americans I've
got over I think 40 40 five of them in
the can holographic portraits full
regalia with face paint and the whole
nine yards and uh somehow I inspired uh
uh Sharon McCormick to shoot one which
is cool I think she's a few since then
but okay yeah yeah that's always nice to
see when you can inspire people to you
know to do something and uh even if it's
what you do it's you know if maybe
they'll do it better you know you never
know MH but uh but it that's it's it's a
cool thing and uh so those are those are
shot um
um I started putting together the
elements for a documentary and uh that's
why I threw up the so-called holoid so
if anybody wants to see the old gers of
holography when they were younger uh
they can go to my website and look at
that slideshow you know what I'm talking
about Frank uh yes you see that yeah no
I did not click on that to tell you the
truth I'm sitting here thinking that's
one of the first places I'm going to go
as soon as I hang this phone up yeah
so-call holoid I used to shoot Polaroid
photographs I was kind of known as the
the docum maniac for a while and uh
because I used to shoot video and stills
and all kinds of stereograms of
holograms and I've got a whole you know
collection of this stuff which I really
would like to put together as a uh as a
little DVD or some kind of presentation
where people can can delve into it as
deep as they want would make a nice CD
ROM there's a number of CD ROM projects
out there right now for historical
holography I know George is doing one in
Canada he's not done already and uh I've
heard of that and uh I know that there
was some documentary shot in the west
coast in the gal just have done
something which I haven't gotten to
screen yet myself but I'm I'm anxious to
one day and you have a couple video
clips on the website you know from that
from one of the past shows I think
excellent excellent well I have a lot of
this uh you know sort of rare footage in
people's Laboratories and uh some of
like Forest stuff and um things that uh
places that don't exist anymore and some
cases sadly people who don't exist
anymore um uh and so it's going to be
very interesting to call this into um a
story that is uh it's documented but
somehow um entertaining as well you know
you'll find that when you look through
that collection of Polaroids everyone
seems to be smiling a lot I mean
everybody's just so darn happy yeah um
uh so uh uh what I'm hoping to capture
in this video is you know what was it
that that made them all so darn happy at
the time you know were you happy at the
time when you were taking the pictures
oh yeah maybe just rubbed off on them
that's no there was there was a certain
spirit with which uh I don't know if
it's been dampened uh well certainly in
some of the individuals involved but
hopefully not in the uh youngsters yeah
but uh uh uh there's a certain Spirit of
Discovery and uh of the unknown
exploring the unknown that that that is
just man makes you want to you know wake
up in the morning or in the night and
jump in a lab and and and see you know
what will come forth and uh and this is
a